Thank you.
If we can go put up the next slide.
The author of that song, his name is Benjamin William Hastings.
He's probably pretty close to Ryan's age.
Northern Irish songwriter from Belfast who moved to Sydney, Australia.
And became a worship leader in 2013 with Hillsong Worship.
Now, I don't know how many of you are familiar with Hillsong and their journey.
But when the church was first planted in the late 1980s, within 30 years, they had expanded 30 countries, over 150,000 congregants.
In just one year in the U.S., their songs are streamed about 1.1 billion times annually.
Some of you are familiar with the song, What a Beautiful Name, 343 million YouTube views on just that one song.
2019, $93 million of revenue.
This young man, this gifted songwriter, follower of Jesus.
Had reached the pinnacle of his craft, of his ministry.
And then in 2020, one of the most well-known and established pastors in the movement, Carl Lentz, pastor in New York,
an individual who had brought in big-money people, big-name people, celebrities, Grammy-type folks, was fired.
He was let go because of multiple infidelities over decades.
He was accused of sexual abuse, something he denied, although he did admit the infidelity.
And within two years, the founding pastor, Brian Houston,
Huston, sorry,
was accused of concealing sex abuse of minors
and inappropriate relationships with two female staff.
And he resigned.
Within just weeks, nine of the 16 Hillsong churches in the U.S. closed.
Mega churches.
Closed.
Go ahead and click the next slide.
I think Hastings was pulled from the season of silence, or what we often call bravado.
In the season of bravado, the season of silence, it's this sense of, I'm doing this.
In the season of wonder, it's this confidence, I can do this.
But in the season of bravado, it becomes this time when, I'm doing this.
And within weeks, was just yanked from that into the season of darkness,
the season of shattering.
The season of, I don't know if I can do this.
In fact, I can't.
Now, I have to say that on August of 2023, Huston was acquitted of his charges.
And I'm really not here at all to talk about the indiscretions of any of those leaders.
That's, that, I don't know enough about it.
And I would, it would never be my place.
But here is a young man serving God at the pinnacle of his ministry,
who is yanked from it.
Emotionally.
And did you notice some of the words in that song?
Go ahead and click the next slide.
I'm not a lost sheep.
I just feel alone in the flock.
In his commentary about the song, he says this line,
are you finding these songs hard to believe that many people thought that,
that he was talking to his, his congregation, his audiences, his listeners.
And he said, no, no, no, no.
This was, this was my prayer.
I was talking to God.
Because God, I don't know these songs that I'm singing.
And I, if I, I don't know what I believe.
God, are you finding it hard to believe these words that I'm singing to you?
It's incredible.
Dark night of the soul where he can sing,
maybe faith is a gift you wasted on me.
I, my, the longevity of my ministry,
unless it is from some great individuals who,
who decades down do something amazing,
will never touch the kind of impact that this 30 some year old guy has had.
Do you know, they,
they estimate that some 55 million
believers will sing one of their songs this morning in church.
Today.
He goes on to talk about,
I began to question the thing that I felt was a purpose.
And then he said,
and this one really caught me because it's true here, folks.
We're going to be talking about the season of darkness.
These times when God forms something in us that,
that is profound and yet unbelievably painful.
All of you just sang a song about,
oh, make new wine in me and then the power of it.
But you know how that song started.
They, they crush the grapes
to make new wine.
We want new wine.
We don't want the process.
We want the power,
but not the pathway.
He said in his commentary,
a year later,
thankfully I worked through a little bit of it.
And at the end of his commentary,
he said, I,
my song was really faith is,
faith is,
faith,
faith is a gift,
but faith is.
And he says,
why are you holding out on me,
God?
In another song that he wrote at the time of the,
the collapsing of the cathedral,
the spiritual cathedral that had been built in his heart and mind that he'd been
part of,
he talked about the church having concrete cancer in its walls.
And then he said,
I don't care about the failing.
I have enough of that in me.
But the inclination to conceal it just doesn't feel like church.
I have to be honest.
This is a hard message,
but it's a critical message.
Because often we're fed this idea that the season of wonder,
wonder and delight is God's intention for all of us all the time.
And if we're not in it,
somehow we have done something wrong.
That somehow we are missing and,
and we have to change.
And let me tell you folks,
the power of this story is,
as far as I can see,
this was done to him.
And yet the internal reality of a believer who's trying to figure out how is it that God does this.
King David said it this way.
Next slide.
Psalm 10.
One.
You know,
David was a man after.
Yeah.
Do you believe that?
A man after God's own heart.
Why,
oh Lord,
are you standing so far off?
Why do you hide yourself in times of trouble?
Is that true?
No.
Is it emotionally true?
Absolutely.
That David in his own hoisting into a season of darkness,
whether it is his father-in-law or his son chasing him out in the desert,
circumstances are such that it's awful.
How long,
oh Lord,
will you forget me forever?
How long will you hide your face from me?
How long must I wrestle with my thoughts
and every day have sorrow in my heart?
How long will my enemy triumph over me?
Next slide.
Hastings is just a modern day example of something that's been around for a long time.
Asaph was a worship leader in Israel,
probably after David,
the most prolific writer of our Psalms,
so connected with the Holy Spirit that he had the privilege,
the opportunity to write the word of God,
to pen it as God inspired him.
He starts out Psalm 73,
as surely God is good to Israel,
to those who are pure in heart.
He makes a statement of faith.
But for me,
I'm about done.
Me,
as I watch what's going on,
as I continue to do this,
he was where Hastings was.
And by the way,
it's a place that I suspect some of us are.
And if you're not,
you probably will be at some point.
As for me,
my feet came close to stumbling.
My steps had almost slipped.
Hastings has a line in his cathedrals of the Netter Grove,
where he talks,
if the wind starts to blow,
I don't know how much longer I will last.
Folks,
it's a direct reference,
not to the Roman seven man.
Many of us know about the Roman seven man,
but this is the Matthew seven man.
This is where,
where Jesus says to them,
therefore,
everyone who hears these words of mine
and puts them into practice is like a wise man.
And when all this stuff comes,
he stands.
But everyone who hears these words of mine
and does not put them into practice
is like a foolish man
who built his house on sand.
That was the line of the song.
And the rain came
and the streams rose
and the winds blew
and beat against that house
and it fell with a great crash.
Hastings was saying,
man,
that's what I feel like.
That's where I feel that I am.
Ryan mentioned two weeks ago
about Mother Teresa
after giving her life
to the poorest of the poor
in the city of joy
in Calcutta
and the poorest slums they could find,
the place where the water floods
in feet every year
and sewer just runs down the streets
and she's doing medical care
and caring for the poor.
And yet on the night
that she's receiving
the Nobel Peace Prize the next day,
she's in her room
talking to God,
questioning her own relationship
with him.
Next slide.
Asaph,
after he talks about the stuff
that really gave him a problem.
And by the way,
Asaph's problems
are maybe some of yours.
My dark night of the soul
was not those things.
But things that I just couldn't reconcile
in my mind
and in my heart
and in my spirit
and everything,
I was at the wall
and everything I thought I knew
I no longer was sure.
Folks,
the reason we're doing this series
is because so many of us
tend to view that as punishment.
And let me tell you,
as awful as it feels
in the midst of it,
it's a gift.
The season of darkness,
oh Lord,
make new wine in me.
And God says,
okay.
And then we say,
enough wine,
Lord.
I've seen
too many people
because for two decades,
this is what I did with pastors
who walked in the dark night of the soul
and questioned their own faith
and how can I even get up there
and preach it
when I don't know if I believe it?
How can I sing these songs to you, God,
when I don't think you believe
what I'm saying?
How can I do this?
What do I do, Lord?
And the mystics
have taught us
it's actually part of God's formation
because these seasons
are seasons of formation.
God is forming us
and I'm going to try to walk you through
what that looks like
and how that feels.
In verse 13 and 14,
Asaph says,
surely in vain
I've kept my heart pure.
He's questioning.
And washed my hands in innocence
for I have been stricken
all day long
and chastened every morning.
Next slide.
If I had said,
I will speak thus,
behold,
I would have betrayed
the generation of your children.
I can't tell you
how many folks in ministry,
the hardest part of it is,
I can't tell them.
I'm feeling this,
but I can't tell them.
It's almost like a parent
that all of life
is falling apart
and they want to reassure
their children
in the midst of that.
And sometimes
the hardest part
of the dark night
of the soul
is the stuff
that we feel
we can't let out.
Hastings says,
but the thoughts
that I thought
about you
just don't work
like I thought.
Janet Hagberg
talks about
the journey of faith
and the journey of faith
when we go through
this inward journey
where God begins
to purge things
inside our very soul
that we don't even know
is there,
that often God
will take us
to the wall.
And the wall
is something
that we cannot climb over
although we try.
We cannot dig under
We cannot knock over.
We can only be at the wall
because it's a wall
that God has got
to remove.
And to remove it
he wants to use it
in your life,
in your soul
to make you more like Jesus.
St. John of the Cross
put it this way.
Next slide.
As a child grows bigger,
the mother gradually
ceases caressing it.
And hiding her tender love,
she puts bitter aloes
upon her sweet breast,
sets down the child
from her arms
and makes it walk
upon its feet
so that it may lose
the habits of a child
and betake itself
to more important
and substantial occupations.
I guarantee
that no child
likes being weaned.
No child understands
the weaning
that goes on.
No child gets it.
But the mother
in her great love
for her child
does it.
Asaph resolves it
by the way
in his whole
I don't get it.
I don't know what to do.
Next slide.
In verse 17
he says
all of this was true.
I questioned everything
and the only solution
was not that I reasoned it
but that I entered
the sanctuary of God.
That like Job
at the end
of his trial
when God finally shows up
and God speaks to him
for Job
it was enough
because God
was there.
Now here's the deal folks.
God shows up
when he knows
it's best for you.
But in this season
there are times
when God will
hide his presence
to finish in you
the work
that you've asked for.
Make new wine.
To finish the activity
of a purging
of a purification.
You know
God doesn't bless you
with an awareness
of his presence
because of how wonderful
you are.
He does it
because he loves you
and he's answering
your prayer
to be transformed.
The opposite
is also true.
God doesn't withhold
the awareness
of his presence
because you're awful.
No,
he does it
because he loves you.
And he does it
because he's answering
your prayer
to be transformed.
Next slide.
God says it
in Isaiah
this way.
I will give you
treasures of darkness
and hidden wealth
of secret places
so that you may know
that it is I
the Lord
the God of Israel
who calls you
by your name.
In verse 5
he promises
of this same passage
I will strengthen
you
though you have not
acknowledged me.
Verse 7
I form the light
and create darkness.
I bring prosperity
and create disaster.
I the Lord
do all of these things.
And then in verse 9
the passage
that I'm sure
is familiar
to many of you
does the clay
say to the potter
what are you making?
I remember
watching a message
one time
when it was
a woman
who was speaking
who was a potter
and she's talking
about how God
forms us
but as she did it
she did it at a wheel
and one of these
little step things
and she's spinning
the wheel
and she takes out
this clay
this lump of clay
and she goes
and then she begins
to apply pressure
to it
and as she applies
pressure
she begins
to form things
and yet
as she's doing that
somehow it defaults
and she stops
the wheel
she takes the pot
she takes the clay
and she
again
because she has
a purpose
for the pot
she knows
what she's doing
with the pot
God is a potter
and he's making
you into something
absolutely wonderful
and useful
and beneficial
and making you
ready for union
with him
but sometimes
that new wine
of power
requires a little
pressing
and I hope
I really hope
because I've seen
too many people
who assumed
in the season
of darkness
that somehow
they had
abandoned God
that somehow
they had
walked away
from God
is that possible?
sure
I don't understand
why
Kent did a great job
and Ryan did a great job
of the season
of silence
it can be your fault
but it can be
God's blessing
to you
the season
of desert
yeah you could
really have screwed up
and that's why
you're there
but it might be
God's wanting
to build
an identity
in you
that this is
the way
he does it
so too
is the season
of darkness
next slide
we started
this whole series
with Ecclesiastes
there is a time
for everything
and a season
for every activity
under heaven
he has made
everything
beautiful
in its time
that is a statement
of faith
my friends
particularly
when you enter
into a season
of darkness
a season
when life
is really hard
and God
seems absent
that it's only
by faith
that we can say
but you're still
good God
I know you're good
I don't see it
I don't feel it
I don't experience it
I don't want
what I'm walking
through
but God
you are good
it's a statement
of faith
he has made
everything beautiful
in its time
he's also said
eternity
in the human
heart
that we want
not just
so
I was talking to
someone the other
day about fruit
and you know
you do ministry
because you want
to see fruit
can I get an amen
on that
anybody out there
like
they do what
they do
because they want
to see fruit
I mean you want
to see change
well the Bible
says it this way
fruit that what
remains
I can look out
over the last
couple decades
and I can see
some rotten
stuff out there
fruit that just
God wants
fruit that remains
and so through
the season of
wonder and delight
and the season
of silence
and bravado
the season
of desert
and disillusionment
and yes
even in the
season of darkness
the season
of shattering
where I realize
I can't do it
my false pride
is removed
okay
next slide
you've seen this
before I think
I've talked to you
about it
by the way
lest you think
Johari is some
new age word
Johari window
came from the
two guys who
created the idea
Joseph and Harry
so
just so we're
clear
two psychologists
and they said
the reality is
in our own
development
there are areas
that are known
to ourself
and known to
others
I'm a pastor
and I know it
and you guys
know it
I have certain
abilities
and I have
certain liabilities
and some of them
you know
and I know
open to
self
known to self
known to others
then there's that
area that is
like known to
everyone else
but not known
to you
you know
God gives
every group
a person
who will
teach you
grace
in small
groups
we often
refer to this
as the EGR
extra grace
required
and if
God
God will give
you one
and it's
part of his
forming
and they always
say you know
if you don't
know who your
EGR is in
your group
it's probably
you
it's known
to others
but it's a
blind spot
we don't
see it
and we all
have them
and then there's
this hidden
area where
it's known
to me
but man
I don't let
anyone else
see it
and then in
the Jahari
window
there is
this unknown
spot
I don't
see it
others
don't see
it
and I
think
we should
correct
I don't
want to
rewrite
Jahari's
window
but if
I were
to do
this
I would
call that
known only
to God
that there
is stuff
that is
known only
to God
and God
will use
the dark
night of
the soul
to bring
it up
and get
it out
the words
purgation
to let
it out
you know
what purging
means right
to get
it out
you don't
even know
it
but it's
something that
God does
in 600
AD
Gregory
the first
compiled
a list
of seven
biblical
sins
and then
in his
message
he called
them deadly
and so
they've been
passed down
through the
ages as
the seven
deadly
sins
St. John
of the
cross
connected
these
seven
deadly
sins
to
the dark
night of
the soul
and God's
purpose in
using the
dark night
of the soul
I'm going
to read
just a short
little section
of my own
writing
relative to
this
to prune
these
imperfections
unknown
places
we become
passive
recipients
of God's
purgation
as he
plunges us
into a
season of
darkness
he takes
us at
our word
and grants
us the
growth we
pursue
by excising
hidden aspects
of our
character
in place
of pride
God builds
humility
in place
of secret
greed
he morphs
it into
simplicity
wrath
and luxury
and gluttony
and envy
and sloth
are divinely
replaced with
contentment
peace
moderation
joy
and strength
Saint John
of the cross
writes this
go ahead
next slide
by the way
he talks
about two
nights of the
soul
and the
first one
is one
that God
invites
everyone
into
and that's
the one
that I'm
going to
read about
here
it's this
place where
these unknown
things need
to be made
known
and they're
made known
in this
place of
darkness
the treasure
of darkness
a place
that's only
known to
God
and comes
to light
so that
he can
begin to
take what
is a secret
pride
and turn
it into
true
biblical
humility
I remember
watching a
message one
time by a
guy he was
talking about
the old
man
and as
he was
preaching
there was
this guy
hanging on
him
so he's
walking around
dragging this
guy that's
just hanging
on him
as the
old man
and as
he begins
to pray
you can see
this old
man getting
weaker
and as
he begins
to confess
the word
of God
you can see
this old
man getting
weaker
as he begins
to submit
to the Lord
the old
man
and he gets
to the place
where finally
the old man
just falls off
him and is
laying on
the ground
like dead
and he
turns back
he goes
whew
glad I got
rid of him
and the old
man went
because there
is this
secret pride
St. John
writes this
at the beginning
as these
beginners
feel themselves
to be very
fervent
and diligent
in spiritual
things
and devout
exercises
there often
comes to
them
through their
imperfections
a certain
kind of
secret pride
some degree
of satisfaction
with their
works
and with
themselves
they condemn
others
in their
heart
when they
see that
they have
not the
kind of
devotion
which they
themselves
desire
when I was
a young
believer
there was a
song I used
to sing
and it was
when I was in
the season of
delight
and at the
end of my
message
Marissa is
going to come
back up
and invite you
to sing it
with me
it's a
prayer
if you're
over 60
and you've
been in
the church
a long
time
you probably
know this
if you're
under 40
you probably
don't
but spirit
of the living
God
fall afresh
on me
spirit
of the living
God
fall afresh
on me
break
me
melt
mold
me
fill
and I can
tell you
when I was
living in
the season
of wonder
and delight
feeling
I'd gotten
so close
to God
because I'd
made so much
progress
feeling so
good about
my relationship
with him
I was all
in
and I would
pray that
song
I would
sing it
to the
Lord
oh Lord
break me
and melt
me
and mold
and fill
me
and sometimes
they add
the word
use me
oh Lord
do it
and then
he did
it
and I
stopped
singing
it
it's like
suffering
is so cool
until you
suffer
persecution
sounds wonderful
until you're
persecuted
at the end
we're going
to invite
you if you
want to
sing that
with us
if you
don't
that's
fine
but here's
the deal
next slide
St. John
says
for however
assiduously
the beginner
practices
the mortification
in himself
of all
these actions
and passions
of his
he can never
completely succeed
very far
from it
until God
shall work
in him
passively
by means
of purgation
of the
said night
in other
words
to make
new wine
you got
to crush
some grapes
St. John
of the cross
in dark
night of the
soul
it's often
called
dark night
of the
senses
unpacks
this by
the way
in about
25 pages
if you
really want
to read
about how
God works
through the
seven sins
biblical sins
that Gregory
identified
and called
deadly
and you
want to
see how
this works
about 25
pages of
reading
you'll come
away
convicted
and
submissive
to the
Lord
if you're
open
to the
spirit
of God
as you
read
I would
commend
it
to you
but he
also talks
about a
second
night
go ahead
and go
there
next
slide
and I'm
not going
to talk
about the
second
dark
night
if you
want to
learn
again
St. John
offers it
and does
a good
job
but the
point that
he makes
and I think
he is right
looking at
history
and looking
at people
looking at
how God
seems to
work
that this
first night
of the soul
dark night
where God
gets in
and begins
to purge
stuff that's
inside our gut
and needs
to come out
and it
requires
this
sickness
to
finally
overcome
the
reflux
to reflect
the activity
keep it
down
and up
it comes
and out
and there
are appropriate
ways to do
that
and good
ways to do
that
and God
I'll give you
an example
my kid
was
one
one and a
half
something like
that
and I
don't know
how she
got it
but she
got a
bottle of
iodine
and she
drank the
whole sucker
and so
I you know
I first
of all
I yelled
for Lori
and she
got mad
at me
that I
yelled at
her
and then
she thought
no wait
Matt
doesn't
normally
yell at
me
maybe I
should
come
and see
what's
going
on
but I
ended up
calling
the nurse
online
and she
said do
you have
this stuff
that makes
a child
throw up
and I
said yes
we do
go get
it
start giving
it to
you know
if this
happens
with
Catherine
this is
what you
want to
do
if this
happens
you want
to bring
her right
to the
emergency
room
I was
only about
five blocks
from the
emergency
room
but if
you can
get it
all up
and get
it out
that would
be good
and so
a loving
father
is giving
my daughter
this stuff
to drink
that's making
her throw
up
and at
some point
she made
the connection
and it
rocked her
boat
because how
could a
loving dad
make her
drink
something
that makes
her feel
that sick
that iodine
wasn't too
bad
it's a
dark night
of the
soul
she didn't
get it
but she's
healthy because
of it
the second
dark night
however
he likens
to
the first
dark night
is like
the pruning
of a
tree
awful
and horrible
and painful
but the
second
dark night
is like
the digging
out of the
roots
and he
says there
are few
who are
invited
into this
in some
ways folks
it almost
parallels
martyrdom
and you
know
there's
a few
rules
about
martyrdom
in the
Christian
world
number
one
never
seek
it
the early
church
at the
time
when people
were
martyred
for their
faith
they condemned
anyone
who would
try in
grandiosity
to create
a situation
so they
could become
a martyr
it's just
pride
never ever
seek
it
and in
fact
if you
read
Jesus
at the
end
when God
said
okay
it's
time
he laid
down
his
life
but there
are a bunch
of times
where he
said
nope
and he
conveyed
himself
right away
from the
crowd
because he
didn't
seek it
until God
said
it's a
gift
so like
martyrdom
the second
night
don't ever
seek it
don't think
somehow I'm
going to
get a
shortcut
to holiness
but if
you're there
and it's
possible that
someone's
there
choose to
believe what
you learned
in the
light
as you
doubt
in the
darkness
I used
to say
never doubt
in the
darkness
what God
revealed
in the
light
I no
longer
say that
because
it's
just
not
real
not if
you're
in the
dark
night
of the
soul
not if
you're
taken to
that
place
where
the
grape
is
being
crushed
so
wine
can
be
made
not
if
you're
in
that
place
where
you're
being
broken
and
melted
molded
and so
now
I think
it's
more
choose
faith
in the
midst
of your
unbelief
choose
to believe
what you
learned
in the
light
as you
doubt
in the
darkness
I'm
going to
say this
and maybe
I'll get
in trouble
from someone
with it
but you
do know
that God
invented
doubt
and he
did so
because he
hates
deception
and all
of us
find ways
and means
to self
deceive
and so
it's through
a gift
of even
doubt
in the
midst
of that
not doubt
of
him
that's
where we
have faith
in him
but in
the things
that we're
sure we
believe
and know
when I
was a
young
believer
I had
a lot
of
doctrines
that I
was
absolutely
sure
on
and I
was
going to
convince
you
of
them
and now
I
have
a few
who
Jesus
is
non-negotiable
fully God
fully man
the Trinity
non-negotiable
the Bible
is the
inspired
authoritative
word
of God
what it
claims
for itself
non-negotiable
but there's
a whole
bunch
of other
things
that I
was
absolutely
sure
about
that I
now realize
maybe I was
right
maybe I'm
wrong
I don't
know
and the
last thing
I would
say
as you
choose to
believe
what you
learned in
the light
while you
doubt in
the darkness
if you're
in this
season
the church
does not
do a
good job
with you
generally
we just
don't
we
call it
unfaith
we call it
backsliding
and we call it
all kinds
of things
we're like
Job's
comforters
what did
you do
wrong
and we
quote
Scripture
like Job's
comforters
but here's
the deal
if you're
there folks
if one of
you's there
two of
you there
don't take
this journey
alone
secrets
kill
find
find a
safe
and
trusted
soul
friend
don't
walk it
alone
there's
something about
one another
that's all
I'm going to
say about
the second
dark night
if
when we're
done
if you're
there
and you
want to
talk
I will
make myself
available
so I hope
you got
the main
message
that
those times
when
when life
is hard
and God
seems absent
it could be
you've done
something wrong
and you
need to
repent
that's
possible
but don't
jump there
I can't
use the
verse out
of Romans
chapter 8
verse 1
there is
now therefore
no
for those
the evil
one loves
to condemn
us
we love
to condemn
us
God loves
to transform
us
and so
if you are
there
I hope
you can hear
that even
this can be
a gift
from God
the treasure
of darkness
that he
spoke about
in Isaiah
but then
what do
you do
with it
I'd like
to give
you two
spiritual
disciplines
in the midst
of this
first of all
most of
it's
passive
and so
one of the
songs we sang
about
the anchor
in our
faith
in many
ways
the
disciplines
that work
in these
seasons
of formation
because we're
a passive
recipient
rather than
an active
discipline
it's more
of an
anchor
it's holding
on to
those things
that we
know
are true
because it's
so clear
in the Scriptures
that they're
true
and what we
experience
as real
is not
necessarily
what God
knows
is true
and we
choose
truth
over what
seems
real
it's an
anchor
of the
soul
but there
are
two
active
exercises
smart
bombs
that can
get at
this time
and if
you're
there
I want
to offer
them
to you
as ways
to begin
to get
at it
the first
one
is praise
praise
is an
act
of declaring
what is
true
whether you
feel it's
true
or not
put on
the garment
of praise
for the
spirit
of heaviness
that there
is this
and I
generally
recommend
that if
people
put on
the garment
of praise
for the
spirit
of heaviness
don't pray
the songs
about how
I love
you Jesus
just pray
the songs
about who
he is
you know
a mighty
fortress
is our
God
a bulwark
never
failing
how great
is our
God
whatever
songs
speak
to his
greatness
because
that's
not
none of
that is
contingent
on how
I feel
it's
just
true
and so
beginning
to offer
those truths
back to
God
in praise
somehow
it affects
our soul
but there's
a second
one
and it's
the one
that I've
shown you
several times
on the
slides up
here
and that's
a practice
of lament
if we'll
go to the
next slide
writing a
lament
I encourage
people if
if they're
just
life is
hard
and God
seems
absent
and take
that
authentic
honest
song
like
Hastings
man
I'm
wondering
if I'm
on sand
if the
wind blows
I don't
know if
I'm
going to
make it
but here's
some critical
pieces of
lament
number one
writing a
lament
is always
to the
Lord
it's like
shooting an
arrow
folks
I was
with
Mike
Gad
out in
Colorado
and we
were
doing the
bow
stuff
I don't
shoot
arrows
I can
talk
about
it
but I
don't
really
do
it
and so
I'm
looking
down
with
my bow
and my
arrow
and I
have it
notched
and Mike
says something
and I
what Mike
and Mike
was very
gracious
he actually
looked at
the person
who's supposed
to be
like supervising
this whole
thing
and he's
just like
looking at
her
and looking
at her
at me
and she
said
Matt
would you
please
point
that
down
the
thing
rule
number
one
bow
and arrow
only
shoot
at the
intended
target
and in
a lament
the target
is always
God
it was
David's
target
to the
Lord
with
feeling
be honest
emotional
truth
to the
Lord
with
feeling
without
censoring
I don't
know if
any of
you have
ever read
C.S.
Lewis's
A Grief
Observed
it's his
lament
by the way
if you don't
know who
C.S.
Lewis is
great
Christian
thinker
great
writer
love
the Lord
and yet
when his
wife
was dying
he had
this lament
inside
this poison
and in
his lament
this man
of
unbelievable
brilliance
laments
to God
and
publishes
it
and
calls
God
a
cosmic
sadist
now does
he think
that's
what God
is
no
is that
what he's
feeling
without
censoring
I've
done this
a hundred
times
with
pastors
and
we
often
ask them
to read
it to
God
in front
of a
trusted
brother
or a
trusted
sister
and
when
we
tell
him
without
censoring
we
say
if
it's
in
there
God's
already
heard
it
so go
ahead
and
write
it
after
the
third
F-bomb
people go
oh I
guess
he
really
means
this
because
if
it's
in
there
God's
already
heard
it
you're
not
going
to
write
a
lament
oh
thou
great
and
gracious
God
thou
dost
take
care
of
me
in
the
midst
of
my
pain
no
Lord
would
you
rip
the
heart
out
of
that
scum
sucking
pig
because
if
it's
in
there
it's
got
to
come
up
and
it's
safety
if
you're
going
to
choose
write
a
lament
I'd
encourage
you
to
write
it
alone
write
it
to
God
write
it
without
censoring
but
write
it
honest
even
if
that
means
when
you're
done
going
to
just
in
your
room
read
burn
it
now
I'm
going
to
encourage
presence
of
a
brother
or
sister
who
is
safe
and
trustworthy
because
confessing
our
faults
one
to
another
does
bring
healing
it
does
bring
healing
but
I
would
rather
you
write
the
honest
mother
Teresa
writes
this to
her
confessor
on
July
3rd
in
the
darkness
Lord
that
you
should
forsake
me
the
child
of
your
love
and
now
has
become
the
most
hated
one
the
you
have
thrown
away
as
unwanted
unloved
I
call
and I
cling
I
want
and
there
is
no
one
to
answer
no
one
on
whom
I
can
cling
no
one
alone
in
the
darkness
I
am
alone
unwanted
forsaken
the
loneliness
of the
heart
that
wants
love
is
unbearable
where
is
my
faith
even
deep
down
right
in
there
is
nothing
but
emptiness
and
darkness
my
God
how
painful
is
this
unknown
pain
it
pains
without
ceasing
I
have
no
faith
I
dare
not
utter
the
words
and
thoughts
that
crowd
my
heart
without
ceasing
I
have
no
faith
I
suffer
in
untold
agony
so
many
unanswered
questions
live
within
me
I'm
afraid
to
uncover
them
because
of
the
blasphemy
if
there
be
God
please
forgive
me
before
the
work
started
there
was
so
much
union
and
love
faith
trust
prayer
sacrifice
did
I
make
the
mistake
of
surrendering
blindly
to
the
call
of
the
sacred
heart
the
work
is
not
a
doubt
because
I'm
convinced
that
it
has
nothing
to
do
with
me
I
don't
feel
not
even
a
single
simple
thought
or
temptation
enters
my
heart
to
claim
anything
in the
work
of
choice
she
later
came to
see that
God was
answering
her
prayer
that
she
could
follow
the
Lord
by
picking
up
her
cross
and
following
him
she
wrote
that
and
shared
it
with
her
confessor
and
it
was
only
published
about
three
years
ago
do
it
in
safety
but
also
do
it
while
listening
so
many
of
the
lament
psalms
start
with
oh
God
where
are
you
and
somehow
in
the
midst
of
pouring
it
all
out
they
find
God
they
speak
a
word
of
epiphany
a word
of
praise
it's
again
like
if
you're
really
sick
you
never
feel
better
than
right
after
you
throw
while
listening
in
faith
next
week
we're
going
to
conclude
this
series
we
don't
want
to
end
with
a
season
of
darkness
because
your
current
season
is
not
your
last
season
God
moves
you
through
various
seasons
and
he
does
do
for
various
means
and
ways
I've
had the
privilege
of
walking
through
the
season
of
darkness
and
emerging
on the
other
side
I've
had
the
gift
of
being able
to enter
back
into that
early
season
of
wonder
and
delight
God
I
don't
know
what
sure
that
seasons
change
God
will
accomplish
what
he
wants
to
accomplish
in
the
midst
of
what
you're
going
through
and
walking
through
and
then
the
season
will
change
if
you
want
Marissa
is
going
to
lead
us
in
a
song
I'd
like
to
ask
you
to
stand
with
me
spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
afresh
on
me
break
melt
me
mold
fill
me
get
all
the
junk
out
that
what
I'm
full
of
is
the
spirit
of
God
if
you're
not
ready
to
pray
the
prayer
then
just
listen
don't
sing
but
if
you're
ready
to
pray
the
prayer
now
that
doesn't
mean
he's
going
to
take
you
to
season
of
darkness
he
might
have
a
totally
different
idea
but
the
question
is
am I
willing
to
go
where
you
want
to
go
Lord
am
I
willing
to
pray
it
as a
song
I
think
Marissa
you'll
sing
through
it
once
and
then
we'll
be
able
to
sing
with
you
if
want
prayer
there
is
this
room
over
here
if
curtain
looks
a little
creepy
to
you
there
are
chairs
up
front
because
I
don't
want
you
traveling
this
journey
alone
I
want
God
to
complete
his
work
in
the
midst
of
safety
and
companionship
we
have
people
who
have
been
trained
to
pray
with
you
they're
not
going
to
try
fix
you
they're
not
going
to
give
unsolicited
advice
I'm
just
going
to
pray
Marissa
lead
us
please
Spirit
of
the
living
God
Fall
fresh
on
me
Spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
fresh
on
me
melt
mold
me
fill
use
me
Spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
fresh
on
me
I'm
going
to
sing
with
Marissa
and I
invite
you
to
as
well
keep
my
microphone
off
while I
sing
Spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
fresh
on
me
Spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
fresh
on
me
melt
Mold
me
fill
use
me
Spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
fresh
on
me
Spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
fresh
on
me
Spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
fresh
on
me
Melt
Mold
me
Fill
Use
me
Spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
fresh
me
on
let me
proclaim
a benediction
over you
a truth
about God
no matter
what season
you're in
and let me
invite you
if you want
prayer to
that you can
either stay
in your seat
or you can
come forward
or come
into the
room
if you're
not staying
I would ask
that you
go quietly
give space
to people
who might
want to
Jude
writes
the brother
of our
Lord
now unto
him
who is
able
to keep
you
and to
cause you
to stand
before
his
presence
blameless
and with
great joy
to the
only wise
God
our
savior
through
Jesus
Christ
our
Lord
be glory
and
majesty
dominion
and
power
both
now
and
forevermore
amen
you may
go in the
nurture and the
admonition of
the Lord
Jesus
Christ
so melt
me
mold
fill
me
use
spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
fresh
on
me
spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
fresh
on
me
spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
fresh
on me
me oh man
melt me
mold me
fill me
use me
mount me
mold me
fill me
and use me
me
spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
fresh
on
me
spirit
of
the
living
God
fall
fresh
on
me
oh
on me, oh, fall fresh on me.
Amen.